Right, so I keep saying long term I said this
multiple times in the earlier lectures also,
but what really is long term right.
So we will try to quantify that now right,
by introducing the notion of something called
return right, so this is a common notation
that I will use throughout where T indicates
the timestamp of the end of the episode T
means the end of the episode right essentially
I have reached S plus right, so this could
this is the most natural way of thinking about
long term return correct, is the most natural
way of thinking about long-term return and
if there, if that T is actually finite right,
so this is actually is not a bad idea and
I will sum up all the reward I'm going to
get in the future and I will try to optimize
that, okay.
So again you can see that if I try to optimize
each one of these individually what will happen
I might get a very high R t plus 1 and R t
plus 2 but it might put me in such a bad S
t plus 2 from then on even if I behave optimally
individually for each of this these numbers
might be small, right. So what I really want
to do is behave in such a way that even if
some of these numbers are small right overall
in the future the sum that I am going to get
should be the maximum, right.
So overall sum should be maximum, so that
is essentially the goal that I have here,
okay so this is fine it works fine there is
one circumstance where this would not work
when T is I mean there is no end right, so
I just keep doing this for forever if I keep
solving a problem forever then it becomes
a problem and not necessarily forever if I
am also doing something over a very, very,
very long horizon if T is very large not necessarily
infinite but T is very large also I get into
some issues, okay because this will become
quantity with a large variance, okay. So one
other thing I should point out this is something
which people miss and get confused sometimes
while reading on their own so T here is a
random variable, right.
So every time I run the system it might stop
at a different time right think of playing
chess right, there is a finite endpoint chess
will end, but every time I play the game I
do not stop at the same number of moves, right
even something like tic-tac-toe right. Even
though there is an upper limit on the number
of moves you can make right, it is not necessary
that you will always end up playing five moves
that you might end you might win in four moves
you might win in well yeah, if you win in
three moves well, okay.
The opponent is really bad but so you could
win in three moves you could win in four moves
or you could win in five moves, right or you
cannot win at all I mean so you could still
end up drawing the game so like that so T
is a random variable so when I put T here
does not mean it always runs for some T steps
okay, so every time I run it will be a different
value for T so remember that, right and consequently
G t is also a random variable because all
of these are random variables I am talking
about sums of random variables, okay.
And a random number of those random variables
are being summed up okay, so Gt is also a
random variable that denotes the return okay,
great. So another notion of return that people
typically use is right, in fact I can even
do that, okay. So go back and think about
it purely from a mathematical perspective
so if my sum is going to run till infinity
and the gamma is less than 1 and remember
that each individually each r is bounded okay,
so this sum will converge to something finite
so I do not have to worry about what I had
in this case this sum will not explode okay,
so that is fine, right.
But there is even something more interesting
about this discounted reward formulation,
in fact originally when people proposed a
discounted reward formulation it was not really
from the boundedness point of view it was
more from a
from a psychology point of view immediate
gratification versus delayed gratification,
right so if you let us look at what happens
if gamma is 0. All thing will go right, it
is just R t plus 1 this goes back to just
optimizing for the immediate payoff, right
so this gives you essentially you are going
to behave in a way so that the next time step
what is the maximum reward that you are going
to get so you are going to behave only in
that way, right.
So if you think about what gamma is doing
so it is making suppose I get a 10 here versus
getting a 10 here so 10 here is more valuable
than 10 here right, of course 10 here is more
valuable than 10 here, right. So let us go
back to our robot grasping problem we are
talking about having a minus 1 all the time
and then giving you 100 when you actually
grasp so instead of that I can say I am going
to use the discounted rewards my gamma is
say 0.8 so what does it mean, so the sooner
I grasp it the larger the value I am going
to see, correct.
So the overall reward I am starting from here
I should put myself in a trajectory so that
I grasp this quickly. Otherwise I will see
some gamma power 10,000 into 100, so that
is very, very small value so the shorter..
I know I can get rid of the minus 1 right.
So I do not really have to do the minus 1
but then what becomes tricky here we have
to figure out what is the right value of gamma
right, so that becomes tricky.
So this is, so they use this kind of gamma
to control for whether you are a near sighted
agent will be worried about immediate gratification
or whether you are okay delaying the gratification
little bit so that you get a higher payoff
further down the line. You have only 1, 1
payoff right, so just pull
what we do not cumulative rewards so you are
talking about regrets you are talking about
regrets right, you are talking about the total
reward case, right.
So yeah, having a discount there really does
not make sense, right so anyway you are trying
to optimize regret right, so in some case
your gamma is as small as possible right when
you say you are optimizing regret that means
you are trying to keep your gamma as small
as possible so essentially you want all your
winnings to come in one pull right, one pull
I want to be optimal, so that is your optimal
regret case, right.
So when you are trying to do achieve something
like this setting a gamma does not make sense
right, but I mean if you can come up with
a different objective function maybe there
is something that you can think over the entire
learning process, okay. So one thing which
I should point out just let me finish one
thing I should point out is that classically
the RL people right, look at bandit problems
as immediate RL right, I mean the learning
the the whole interaction is just that one
arm pull, okay that is how we think of it
while the, in the long-term case is the full
RL problem.
But if you look at the people who work in
the Bandit theory community right, they think
of the interaction as the entire learning
process, right that they do not think of it
as one arm pull they think of it as the whole
process itself is the learning process so
for them it is like an episode, right so there
is a very different mindset so the other people
do not think of it that way and the bandit
people do not think of discount factors and
other things because that is something which
the RL guys just came up with for looking
at long-term payoffs so there is a mismatch
of vocabulary there so maybe there is something
to find that in the middle ground but I am
not sure.
Return is a function of the time step, yeah
here let us put it this way so I should optimize
my policy in such a way that wherever I am
starting from there and going forward I should
get maximum possible return. So even if I
am in the last step I do not want to goof
up in the last step but if I am see, one thing
you should remember is that if I know where
I am going to end if that capital T is given
to me before hand then it becomes a non-stationary
problem.
Because I know okay, I have five more steps
to go what should I do I take one more step
I have only four more steps to go what should
I do so immediately the problem changes right
if I know the T then it is a non-stationary
setting, right so we will not will not look
at cases where the T is known, okay we will
only look at cases where T is known to be
finite but not deterministic, right it is
not known apriori so it is not like I can
say that I will optimize only at the last
step or anything because I do not know what
the last step is, right.
I might recognize it when I actually reach
it but I do not know beforehand that okay,
I am going to have only so many step steps
to go, I mean this is the normal seeing that
we assume but you can immediately see it is
not realistic you know I mean when you are
playing chess you can always say I am going
to win in three more moves or well I am going
to lose in three moves I mean depending on
right, so how well the game is going. So in
some cases you do have this kind of a little
bit of a forecasting ability as to what the
T is, but typical the basic setup that we
will talk about will assume T is unknown.
Yeah so people understand why gamma equal
to 1, closer to 1 is far sighted, right and
closer to 0 is near sighted clear.
Well, depends on many things right, depends
on the value of gamma and depends on the magnitude
of the other rewards that you are getting
right, so let us say gamma is 0.9999999. Then
the bias is low depending on how far sighted
you want to be you have to pick your gamma,
right yeah they are unsatisfactory you have
another free parameter really free parameter
that you have no way how to tune but yeah
it is there right so we will talk about another
reward formulation shortly.
Which gets rid of the gamma but makes it very
hard to optimize anyway so any other questions
on this. Doesn't matter, Yeah, I just add
it up yeah sure, yeah but then that means
I am fall, I am failing after more time steps,
right so I am okay whether that is positive
or negative it does not matter as far as this
return definitions are concerned, you are
essentially interested in maximizing the return
therefore if you are going to take an action
that gives you a minus 100 reward the farther
out in the future you take it is better, right.
So succeed for as long as you can and then
die you know right, so yeah it does not matter
so the rewards can be positive, negative.
So reinforcement learning is really the community
is little weird right, so we talk about positive
rewards and negative rewards right if you
look at the psychology literature they talk
about rewards and punishments right, for some
reason the RL community and if you look at
the, you know other places they call it payoffs
right or they call it cost negative rewards
are called costs but the RL community somehow
thinks of negative things also as rewarding
so we have positive rewards and you have negative
rewards but in the larger scheme of things
you know negative things also improve your
experience you know they enrich your life
in some way so you can think of negative rewards
also anyway.
So good so this is fine then we will move
on to one more definition I have to give this
right, so what does that do just gives me
the average right, so the more the reward
I accumulate the larger the average is going
to be right so for a finite number of N this
makes sense right, but what if I have an infinite
number of rewards in the future. Under mild
regularity assumptions and bounded-ness of
the individual Rs this will be bounded, okay.
What is not clear is that it will have actually
have a limit, might not right in general it
might not have a limit so you have to impose
additional constraints on the kind of problems
that you are solving not all problems have
this defined right or I mean you can make
some small variations to this to make sure
that all problems have this limit defined,
okay. So there are slight different the limit
can be we can play around with the limit.
For example one case where limit will not
exceed exists is this if the sequence is periodic,
right if the sequence is periodic then the
limit will not exist right, because it will
just keep oscillating all the time, right.
So in this case we use something called the..
do people know how to handle limits of periodic
sequences use something called the cesaro's
limit which essentially looks at the average
over periods and lets the number of periods
run to infinity, right so in the reason the
limit does not exist is because you cut the
sequence in the middle of a period right so
if it is going to be periodic so you only
take a period as a unit and take the reward
over the period, right and then you keep adding
that over subsequent periods and take the
average, right and limit as the number of
such periods you consider it goes to infinity
is called the cesaro's limit.
Then in such cases limit might exist of course
there are bunch of other conditions you have
to put on the actual structure of the problem
itself for you to ensure that this limit exists
but for a very broad class of problems you
can talk about this limits as well. So the
nice thing about this kind of the return definition
is that it does not have a pesky gamma parameter
right so it makes it nice from a computational
point of view not to have the gamma parameter.
But it makes it little weaker from a, one
of the original motivations of RL point of
view because it does not have the gamma parameter,
okay. So gamma parameter allows you to have
you know some sense personality for your agent
right is it a near sighted agent or a far
sighted agent and so on so forth right so
especially people in neuroscience when they
are looking at modeling reinforcement learning
humans right, so they actually have they can
think of estimating what is your gamma by
running experiments with you right.
Because it is kind of you know it is a personality
issue thing right, so some people will tend
to be in fact there are studies that try to
correlate the levels of serotonin in your
head to gamma, right so more the serotonin
the larger the gamma value you have in your
decision making and so on so forth I mean
it is like this is really weird how we seem
to have all these parameters in our head tied
up with the different kinds of neurotransmitters,
right anyway.
So this is called the average reward, this
is called average reward return so any guesses
what this is called discounted return
that sorry hmm I cannot hear, cumulative or
total return on right so if you are going
to call that cumulative then you have to call
this cumulative discounted, okay so there
is a very nice problem that people use for
motivating why discounted return is bad, okay.
So let me let me try and do that here, okay
so I am implying no theological leanings here
okay this is just a fun example, so that is
earth okay that is heaven and that is hell
so the path to heaven has a minus 100 reward
and the path to hell has a plus 1000 reward
right but once you reach heaven you get a
plus 1 infinitely once you reach hell you
get a minus 1 infinitely
I said I am not getting into theology here
okay, this is just a fun example of course
you can always think about other things here,
no reward for ..nahh..anyway you are finished
here right, it is a transient state we do
not care.
But then if I said gamma is 0.1 or something,
right you would prefer going to hell right
if gamma is like 0.9 in fact gamma has to
be pretty high for you to go to heaven right,
so it is the same problem so now gamma becomes
part of the problem definition right, depending
on what value I set for gamma my optimal policy
itself will change right, so this is not a
desirable state of affairs I mean if you are
thinking about saying okay here is a problem
solve it and it turns out that if I use average
reward scenario now which is better going
to heaven is better always does not on depend
on anything what does it depend on.
I am going to get an infinite number of plus
1s right that will thulp any my negative things
I get initially I am getting a finite value
for negative here I am going to get a minus
infinity there and a plus infinity here so
that trumps anything that happens here, so
average reward will tell me that this is the
best thing to do. But if I am going to use
discounted returns so I will go up or down
depending on what my gamma is right. So now
you can immediately see that discounted return
is a more realistic return because not everybody
is going to heaven right anyway that is the
fun part.
We come to the really one of the crux of reinforcement
learning here, right in the full RL and a
lot of the algorithms that we look at and
the notion of a value function. Right we already
looked at the value function right, but the
value function we looked at was very simplistic
right so what did we do there we said okay,
average of all the rewards I obtained so far
right that is the value function then we have
another value which we looked at which is
the expected true expected reward that I should
get if I take an action, right so we denote
that by q star and then we denoted by Q the
average that I am maintaining for this right.
But here we have something more complex, what
do we have here we have a policy pi which
determines not just the current reward but
also the sequence that I am going to see hence
forth right, so when I am going to talk about
a value function here I will talk about something
called V of pi right, so V pi is the value
function associated with a policy pi, right.
So when you say V pi of s, so this is essentially
the expectation of, so what should I be taking
the expectation of
rewards or returns what do you think it is
I should be taking the expectation of the
returns, right.
Because the return is what I am looking to
optimize this is what I should be predicting
so in the bandit case I was only looking at
the reward so I was just making it with the
expectation of the reward right here I should
make it out as the expectation of return so
given anything. Anything else, I need to condition
it on pi right, because I already have a pi
here so why do I need to condition on pi because
my Gt is going to depend on pi. Regardless
of what formulation I am using the subsequent
rewards I am going to get depend on the actions
I take, right so I really need to know what
my pi is right.
So I need to condition it on pi so we will
denote it like this, right when I write the
pi here that means that is a policy I am conditioning
on, okay the expectation with respect to the
distribution generated by following pi okay,
of Gt given that at time t, I started with
state s okay, does it make sense everyone
on board, right so I am starting from state
s I am following pi I am generating one trajectory
right like this right so I start from s okay,
go to some s prime, go to s double prime so
on so every time I take an action so I will
take a, a prime, a double prime and so on
and I will get some r, right this is one trajectory.
So like that I will start from s, I will do
another trajectory then I will start from
s I will do another trajectory, I will start
from s I will do another trajectory then I
will be getting all these rewards like we
have r, r prime, r double prime like that
I will get some r1 prime, r1 double prime
and so on so forth.. each trajectory I will
get one such sequence of rewards right, so
I will add up all of these or I will take
a discounted sum of all of this right, so
I will do that right and I will take the average
that is that essentially whatever that average
will converge to is my expected value for
this, this is essentially what I mean.
When i say Gt such that St equal to s, that
means I will start with s okay, and compute
this rewards okay, right. So is it clear why
we need to condition on the pi as well right
the future is going to depend on pi yeah,
yeah I am talking about the expectation here
I am just explaining to you what the expectation
is so every time I generate the trajectory
through pi right, two things could happen
A I could pick different actions because pi
is stochastic, B the world could change in
a different way because the world is stochastic,
so in the same s I could take the same a,
I might end up in a different s prime every
time right, so there are multiple ways in
which this stochastic can operate so one pi
itself is stochastic therefore in the same
s I need not take the same action again.
Right first time I can take a1, next time
I can take a2 and so on so forth right that
will completely change the trajectory that
will come later or I will take the same a
right, I might end up in a different s prime
because of the transition probability so every
time I do this trajectory I will get some
different trajectory, I mean every time I
generate a trajectory I will get a different
sequence right, and the expectation is over
all such sequences you know what is the total
reward I will get so that is essentially what
is the value function is, okay is it clear
great.
Let us confuse people some more so we had
Q earlier right so what was Q of a, q star
of a was the true thing, Q of a is the expectation,
the expected estimate for taking action a,
right but then here we have to worry about
taking action a in a specific state because
every state it is going to be different, correct
every state it will be different so what this
will be, I will have to do this I still have
to do this, so what is the big difference
between the V and q hmm..sorry, yeah action
a is fixed so earlier when you are generating
trajectories for V pi I said you start with
s right, then you go to s prime then you go
to s double prime and so on so forth and then
you could I said you could pick any action.
So first time I will pick a, then a prime
the next time you put some a1 so
like this right, so you could pick different
actions every time we generated the trajectory.
So now I'm saying you cannot do that right,
so every time I generate the trajectory you
have to pick a first right, but subsequently
you pick actions according to pi, right the
first action is something that is fixed now,
the first action will be a all the time so
what does this tell you it tells you how good
is it to perform action a in a given state.
So earlier you did not have that information
but now you have the information about how
good is it to perform action a in a given
state, okay is
it clear going back and thinking about the
problem itself right. So there is a problem
that we are trying to solve right, so how
do you define the problem how do you characterize
the problem right, so I am in a state s I
take an action okay I go to a next state and
I also get a reward right.
So for me to characterize the problem I need
to tell you how this transitions happen, how
the reward generation happens right, so I
need to really look at this following question
what is the probability of given, sorry.
Rt+1 given is this sufficient I mean think
about it right, riding a bicycle so you probably
need to know what is the velocity momentum
that you had before and it is not enough to
know where you are on the road and how you
are tilting you might want to know something
more about the history of how you got there,
right. So you really need that quantity so
you need to know what is the probability of
St+1 , Rt+1 given everything that went before
that, correct. This becomes a little complex
to model because the number of parameters
you will need for modeling something like
this becomes pretty huge.
So what we typically end up doing is make
a very strong assumption that this guy is
equal to so what you truly need is the first
quantity right, because it becomes very hard
to estimate very hard to define you make the
assumption that that quantity is really equal
to this right so what is this assumption called
typically Markov assumption it is essentially
a first order Markov assumption where the
history does not matter right only the current
state and current action matters that will
determine what the next state and next action
will be right.
So we make a further assumption which is,
what is this assumption I made.. stationarity,
right so we will typically operate in markov
environments right and will typically assume
they are stationary, okay. So for me to characterize
a problem now what should I give you
what I need is what is the question yeah,
to specify the problem what are the things
I should give you okay, I should give you
the states over which the problem is defined
right.
I need to do that right I need to define the
state space over which the problem is defined
and then the set of actions that I can take
and right, the P function right, so I need
all of this to define the problem completely
anything else I need, depends on what is the
return I am using, I might also need
a gamma right if my return, if I am using
a discounted return depending on what the
value of gamma is the problem changes right
that is what we discussed.
So if I am going to use discounted return
I should also specify gamma as part of the
problem, okay is it clear so I need all of
this to define my problem right in some cases
we use a slightly simplified definition where
instead of having the single joint distribution
s over s prime and r right, we also give it
as two separate quantities.
So I will suggest S I mean I have to specify
S, A then I will specify that so what is that
called, sometimes called the transition function
or transition probabilities okay, and then
I will specify the
expected value of the return given that at
t, I was in s, I did action a and I went to
s prime right, so essentially I am writing
this out splitting this up right, so instead
of giving the joint distribution I am saying
okay no, no I will specify the s prime separately
and for the R I will condition it on s prime
also right.
So I can we can think in some sense I am using
the chain rule and splitting that joint probability
as P of s prime into P of r given s a s prime,
but what is the difference here instead of
specifying P of r given s a s prime, I am
giving you only the first moment or zeroth
moment, giving the first moment of the distribution
right, so why is this enough why is this enough
because I am going to be optimizing only the
expected value of Gt, okay and then Gt is
composed of these guys right.
So essentially I will be taking the individual
expectations of each one of these right, and
that is enough for me, I do not really need
to know the distribution which generated these
rewards because individually I will be taking
the expectations of each one of these rewards
and therefore knowing the expectation alone
is enough so sometimes you specify the problem
like this right, and this is typically how
you would I would specify a what is called
a Markov decision process.
So it is a system is a decision system that
you have to for every state you have to actually
keep giving a decision right, and it follows
Markovian dynamics right, both the transition
and the rewards follow, I mean satisfy the
Markov property right, so such a system is
called a Markov decision process right so
we have states you have set of decisions right
and the evolution of the states follows the
Markov process okay so they are called Markov
decision process, okay and what we will assume
is that the reinforcement learning problems
that we are trying to solve can be modeled
as MDPs, okay.
We will assume that the reinforcement problems
you are trying to solve can be modeled as
MDPs so in some sense a value function really
you know is useful only if you have the Markov
property, why because I am assigning a value
to a state regardless of how I got to the
state right, so if the Markov property is
not satisfied how I got to the state will
influence what happens in the future right.
Since I am saying that no I do not care about
what happened in the past I am saying I am
starting in state s okay, I am going to be
following policy pi here after what is the
expected return therefore I am saying history
is irrelevant right, when I am defining a
value function another way of thinking about
it is here the value function is marginalizing
over history so it is essentially taking the
expectation regardless of what the history
was that is one way of looking at it I mean
in some cases that is how you make sense out
of the value functions.
Because as we go along later we will see that
we actually apply RL blindly to problems that
are non-Markov right and we will be using
the V function and the q function in such
cases. So the only way to make sense out of
what is happening in such cases is to say
that hey we are essentially marginalizing
the history say we are just doing the taking
the expectation over all possible histories
as well, it may or may not be a sensible quantity.
But if it works hey..you just use it right,
but normally your value function makes sense
only if you have the Markov property forget
about the future right, then the because you
are ignoring the past it makes sense only
if you have the Markov property right, does
it make sense right so that is why I was saying
that I should have probably defined value
functions after telling about Markov decision
processes but it is okay, you can still understand
it in the general sense as well great. So
the next thing we have to talk about is optimal
value functions, right that I will start that
in the next class.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved